Finding Aid for Leon DeMeunier Papers 1960-1964 and 1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Leon DeMeunier papers 1960-1964 and 1971
DeMeunier, Leon
0.8 linear ft.
851131 Aa 2
Chairman of the Detroit Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) from its establishment in 1960 until sometime in 1962 or 1963. Papers include material on the operation of the Detroit chapter of CORE and its role in the national civil rights movement.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Leon DeMeunier donated his papers in 1971. Donor number 5115
The collection is open for research.
Leon A. DeMeunier was chairman of the Detroit Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) from its establishment in 1960 until sometime in 1962 or 1963. He was also national council member and member of the executive committee of the Brotherhood of St. Andrew in the United States, a men and boy's organization of the Episcopal Church. As CORE officer, DeMeunier served as participant, organizer, and negotiator for his organization. In the forefront of civil rights protests in this period, CORE sponsored a variety of demonstrations and protests, including lunchroom sit-ins and "Freedom Rides" on buses to the deep South to protest segregated facilities and the denial of service to African Americans.
The Leon A. DeMeunier collection, covering the period of 1960 to 1964, documents the role of CORE in the civil rights struggle of the early 1960s. The focus of the collection is the national civil rights movement and its efforts to overturn the practice of segregation in the South. Although the materials have been donated as a personal collection, the files are those of Detroit CORE with the following series: Papers, Printed Materials, Newspaper Clippings and Magazine Articles, and Miscellanea.
Subjects:
DeMeunier, Leon.; Afro-American civil rights workers--Michigan.; Civil rights--United States.; Civil rights movements--Michigan--Detroit.; Discrimination in employment--Michigan.; Congress of Racial Equality.; Congress of Racial Equality. Detroit (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.)--Race relations.; Southern States.
- Papers, 1960-1963 and 1971
  The Papers series covers the period of 1960 to 1963. There is a single item dated 1971. This series has been arranged chronologically and consists of correspondence, mimeographed materials, notes, organizational mailings, and memoranda. The series concerns the operation of Detroit CORE and the management of its protests.
  - 1960 (Box 1)
  - January-April 1961 (Box 1)
  - May 1961 (Box 1)
  - June 1961 (Box 1)
  - July 1961 (Box 1)
  - August-September 1961 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1961 (Box 1)
  - Undated, 1961 (Box 1)
  - January-April 1962 (Box 1)
  - May-August, 1962 (Box 1)
  - September-December 1962 and undated 1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963and 1971 (Box 1)
- Printed Material
  Printed Materials is a series also arranged chronologically and consisted of leaflets, newsletters of various organizations and groups, and various announcements and programs.
  - 1958-1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961 (Box 1)
  - 1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1964 and undated (Box 1)
- Newspaper clippings and Magazine articles
  The Newspaper Clippings and Magazine Articles series concerns both local and national events relating to CORE and to civil rights in general.
  - 1958-1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961 (Box 1)
  - 1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  Miscellaneous is an arbitrarily constructed file that includes the constitution and bylaws of Detroit CORE, scattered minutes of meetings and reports. Also within this series are pamphlets and publications of various organizations, and some DeMeunier personal items. Also placed here, and illustrative of the time, are two CORE collection canisters no doubt used at rallys and demonstrations.
  - CORE records (Box 1)
    (include constitution and bylaws, minutes of meetings, and various reports)
  - Pamphlets and publications of CORE and other civil rights organizations, 1960-1964 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1961 (Box 1)
    (include tickets, calendar notebook, and receipts)
  - CORE collection cannisters (2)